The Ken Russell Collection
The Ken Russell Collection
1958 - 1993
RUS
Solent University Library
Russell Ken 1927-2011 British film director
1 cabinet (2 linear metres)
Henry Kenneth Alfred Russell, known as Ken Russell, was a British film director. He was born in Southampton, Hampshire, England on 3 July 1927. He began making short films in the 1950s and made several documentaries for the BBC TV arts programme Monitor from 1959-1965. His 1969 film Women in Love, an adaptation of the D.H Lawrence novel, won him an Oscar nomination for Best Director. Several of Russell's films caused controversy for their nudity and portrayal of sexuality, The Devils (1971) probably causing the greatest furore. Other notable films include Tommy (1975) and Altered States (1980). Russell died on 27 November 2011 in Lymington, Hampshire, England.
The collection principally consists of still photographs taken on the sets of several of Russell's films; also included are scripts, videotapes, promotional materials for some of Russell's works, and miscellaneous other materials such as programmes for film festivals and film equipment (a light, a clapperboard, film tins).
The collection is organised alphabetically by title of the production, with items unrelated to a production at the end. It is not known whether this was the original arrangement.
All items in the collection are to be retained permanently.
Further accruals are not expected.
The collection was donated by Ken Russell. The precise date of the donation has not been recorded, but it is likely to have around 2000, and is certainly no later than 2002.
Donation
Access is by appointment only. Please email: library.support@solent.ac.uk
Television--Great Britain--History--20th Century; Screenwriting; Filmmaking; Motion picture producers and directors; Russell Ken 1927-2011 British film director
- Film, TV, Stage, and Radio Productions, 1962 - 1986; RUS/1; Solent University Library; 1 cabinet (266 wallets)
  Material relating to Russell's film, television, and radio works, principally consisting of still photographs taken on the sets of these works, but also including scripts and videotapes.
  Most entries in this series include a printed page (from Film Index International, or IMDB) giving details of the production (date, crew, cast); some of these are dated (November 2000). It is assumed, but not known, that these were printed by repository staff when the collection was originally arranged.
  - The ABC of British Music, 1988; RUS/1/2; Solent University Library; Farrell Simon Photographer; 3 items
    Three black and white photographs related to Ken Russell's documentary The ABC of British Music, which was broadcast by London Weekend Television on February 4, 1988. Two photographs are of the filming process, and are attributed in pencil to Simon Farrell. The third could be a still from the film.
    IMDB page for The ABC of British Music
    Farrell Simon Photographer
  - Alice in Russialand, 1993 - 1995; RUS/1/1; Solent University Library; Meadows Daniel b 1952 Photographer; 24 items
    Items relating to the film Alice in Russialand, written and directed by Ken Russell.
    Detailed contents:
    - 3 typewritten scripts for Alice in Russialand, one dated 15.4.93.
    - 1 shooting schedule, dated 15.4.93
    - 20 colour slides appearing to show scenes from the film, and attributed to Daniel Meadows.
    IMDB page for Alice in Russialand
    Meadows Daniel b 1952 Photographer
  - Altered States, 1980; RUS/1/3; Solent University Library; 79 items
    Items relating to Ken Russell's film Altered States.
    - 12 miniature (approximately 30 X 25 cm) promotional posters for the film.
    - 33 black and white photographs, 32 apparently stills from the film, 1 showing Russell on set.
    - 34 colour photographic slides, apparently stills from the film.
    IMDB page for Altered States
  - The Boyfriend, 1971 - 1972; RUS/1/4; Solent University Library; 73 items
    Items relating to Ken Russell's 1971 musical comedy The Boyfriend, an adaptation of Sandy Wilson's 1953 musical of the same title.
    - 72 black and white photographs, most apparently stills from the film, possibly some from the filming process, one showing Russell copyrighted to MGM 1972.
    - a promotional booklet for the film.
    IMDB page for The Boyfriend
  - Billion Dollar Brain, 1967; RUS/1/5; Solent University Library; Jay John 1920-2005 Photographer; 102 items
    Material relating to Ken Russell's film Billion Dollar Brain, an adaptation of Len Deighton's novel of the same title.
    - 101 black and white photographs taken during filming and breaks from filming. Many are attributed to John Jay; some show Russell himself, most are of the actors; one shows Russell's wife, Shirley, with their three sons, and has a note to "Mama Russell" on the back.
    - A promotional booklet ("Exhibitor's Campaign Book") for the film (11 pages)
    IMDB page for Billion Dollar Brain
    Jay John 1920-2005 Photographer
  - Clouds of Glory, 1978; RUS/1/6; Solent University Library; 7 items
    Photographs showing Russell directing William and Dorothy, one of the episodes of Clouds of Glory.
    IMDB page for Clouds of Glory
  - Crimes of Passion, 1984; RUS/1/7; Solent University Library; 10 items
    Black and white photographs taken from the making of Russell's film Crimes of Passion. Most photographs appear to show scenes from the film, one shows Russell directing.
    IMDB page for Crimes of Passion
  - Dante's Inferno, 1967; RUS/1/8; Solent University Library; Konig George Photographer; 11 items
    Black and white photographs relating to Russell's film Dante's Inferno, broadcast by the BBC on 22 December 1967 as part of the documentary series Omnibus. One photograph appears to be a still from the film; the others, some of which are attributed to George Konig, may have been taken during filming.
    IMDB page for Dante's Inferno
    Konig George Photographer
  - The Death of Alexander Scriabin, 1995; RUS/1/9; Solent University Library; 4 items
    Four copies of scripts for The Death of Alexander Scriabin, a radio play by Ken Russell about the Russian composer and pianist, broadcast in June 1995 on BBC Radio 3.
  - Debussy, 1963; RUS/1/10; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Two photographs taken from the making of Russell's film Debussy.
    - A photograph of Victoria Russell, Ken Russell's daughter, 18 months old, with the actor Oliver Reed.
    - Apparently a photograph of a scene from the film.
    IMDB page for Debussy
  - The Devils, 1971; RUS/1/11; Solent University Library; 97 items
    Photographs relating to Russell's film The Devils.
    92 sheets (each sheet with multiple photographs) of colour photographs taken from the filming process.
    5 black and white photographs apparently showing stills from the film, 3 of which appear to be promotional material.
    Six of the sheets of photographs are held in the third (oversize) drawer in the cabinet.
    IMDB page for The Devils
  - The Diary of a Nobody, 1964; RUS/1/12; Solent University Library; 3 items
    Three black and white photographs taken during the filming of The Diary of a Nobody, Russell's film based on the novel by George and Weedon Grossmith.
    IMDB page for The Diary of a Nobody
  - Double Exposure, 1994; RUS/1/13; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A treatment by Ken Russell for an episode of The South Bank Show discussing the lives of composer's widows. The treatment is titled Double Exposure, but it was broadcast as Classic Widows by ITV on 5 February 1995.
  - Elgar's Land of Hope, 1976; RUS/1/14; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A script (56 pages) for Elgar's Land of Hope, "a screen story by Ken Russell". It is dated 21 January 1976, and is to be distinguished from Russell's 1962 documentary about Elgar. It is unclear whether the script was ever made into a production.
  - French Dressing, 1963; RUS/1/15; Solent University Library; 24 items
    24 black and white photographs relating to Ken Russell's film French Dressing, apparently including stills from the film and photographs taken on set, which are labelled "to be returned to Chris Wicking," possibly the photographer.
    IMDB page for French Dressing
  - Gothic, 1986; RUS/1/16; Solent University Library; 9 items
    Photographs (6 colour, 3 black and white) taken from Ken Russell's film Gothic.
    IMDB page for Gothic
  - Immortal Beloved, 1985 - 1989; RUS/1/17; Solent University Library; Anderson Jo; 3 items
    Three scripts of the film Immortal Beloved, written by Ken Russell and Jo Anderson.
    IMDB page for Immortal Beloved
    Anderson Jo
  - The Insatiable Mrs Kirsch, 1993; RUS/1/18; Solent University Library; Baynes Hetty 1956-; Bourdillon Mark Photographer; Stay Still Photography Company; 193 items
    Material relating to the 1995 short film The Insatiable Mrs. Kirsch, written by Ken Russell and Hetty Baynes.
    - 5 copies of a script for the film
    - 1 small envelope of negatives
    - 27 colour transparencies of photographs taken during filming, showing both Russell and (apparently) scenes from the film, attributed to Mark Bourdillon.
    - 159 colour slides taken during filming, showing both Russell and (apparently) scenes from the film, attributed to Stay Still.
    - 1 colour photograph, apparently showing Russell and his family.
    IMDB page for The Insatiable Mrs. Kirsch
    Baynes Hetty 1956-; Bourdillon Mark Photographer; Stay Still Photography Company
  - Isadora Duncan, the Biggest Dancer in the World, 1966; RUS/1/19; Solent University Library; 37 items
    37 black and white photographs taken from Isadora Duncan, the Biggest Dancer in the World, also called Isadora, which was directed by Russell and broadcast by BBC TV in 1966.
    IMDB page for Isadora Duncan, the Biggest Dancer in the World
  - Lady Chatterley, 1993; RUS/1/20; Solent University Library; 4 items
    Material relating to Russell's film Lady Chatterley, including two black and white photographs of Russell, one with his son Rupert, on set, and two PAL VHS video cassettes (each 120 minutes, made by London Films).
    IMDB page for Lady Chatterley
  - Lisztomania, 1975; RUS/1/21; Solent University Library; Farrell Simon Photographer; 17 items
    Black and white and colour photographs taken from the making of Russell's film Lisztomania. At least one of the photographs is attributed, in pencil, to Simon Farrell.
    IMDB page for Lisztomania
  - Mahler, 1974; RUS/1/22; Solent University Library; Connor Frank Photographer; 40 items
    Material relating to Ken Russell's film Mahler. There are 39 black and white photographs that appear to have been taken during film-making, some possibly showing scenes from the film; some are attributed to Frank Connor. There is also a promotional booklet for the film.
    The booklet is in the third, oversize, drawer in the cabinet.
    IMDB page for Mahler
    Connor Frank Photographer
  - Miscellaneous Photographs: Unknown Sources, approximately 1965 - approximately1985; RUS/1/23; Solent University Library; 12 items
    Twelve black and white photographs apparently taken during the filming of some of Russell's works. It has not been possible to identify the works for these items.
  - Ming Ti: The Lowlander, RUS/1/24; Solent University Library; 2 items
    2 copies extended treatment for Ming-Ti: The Lowlander, "the first 25 minute episode in the 12 part series by Ken Russell." There is no external evidence to suggest that this was ever produced.
  - The Music Lovers, 1971; RUS/1/25; Solent University Library; 17 items
    Material relating to Russell's film The Music Lovers.
    - 8 colour photographs, apparently promotional stills.
    - 6 black and white photographs taken during filming.
    - 3 promotional booklets for the film, one in French, one labelled "Exhibitor's Campaign Book".
    IMDB page for The Music Lovers
  - The Rainbow, 1989; RUS/1/26; Solent University Library; Coote Clive Photographer; 1 item
    An album with approximately 100 colour and black and white photographs from Russell's film The Rainbow, including both scenes from the film and photographs of Russell directing and in breaks from the filming. The album has a dedication: "For Ken, "Thank you for the film that changed my life," lots of love, Clive, 89". The album may well be a gift of Clive Coote, to whom some of the photographs are attributed.
    IMDB page for The Rainbow
    Coote Clive Photographer
  - The Rake's Progress, 1982; RUS/1/28; Solent University Library; 35 items
    35 black and white photographs of on-stage and behind-the-scenes action from Rakes Progress, a production of the Stravinsky opera, directed by Russell, at the Maggio Musicale festival in Florence in 1982.
  - Salome's Last Dance, 1988; RUS/1/27; Solent University Library; Coote Clive Photographer; 4 items
    An album containing 67 photographs (black and white; colour) relating to Russell's film, Salome's Last Dance, including both scenes from the film and photographs of Russell directing and in breaks from the filming. The album is inscribed as from "Clive", and may well be a gift of Clive Coote, to whom some of the photographs are attributed.
    IMDB page for Salome's Last Dance
  - Salome [Opera], 1993; RUS/1/36; Solent University Library; 3 items
    Three copies of a booklet (63 p.), Salome, published by Oper der Stadt Bonn. The publication appears to be designed to accompany a production of Richard Strauss' opera Salome, directed by Russell.
  - Savage Messiah, 1972; RUS/1/29; Solent University Library; 138 items
    Material relating to Ken Russell's film, Savage Messiah, which tells the story of the French sculptor Henri Gaudier-Brzeska.
    - 133 black and white photographs showing scenes from the film and breaks between filming, including shots of Russell giving direction and of Victoria Russell (age 10), daughter of Ken Russell, who had a role in the film.
    - Promotional material for the film: 1 colour photograph, 1 MGM Pressbook, 2 small posters, 1 sheet titled 'Press & Advertising Material for MGM's Savage Messiah.'
    IMDB page for Savage Messiah
  - The Strange Affliction of Anton Bruckner, 1990; RUS/1/31; Solent University Library; 6 items
    Photographs relating to Ken Russell's film The Strange Affliction of Anton Bruckner. All photographs show Russell directing the film. There are two large (approximately 40 x 30 cm) black and white photographs and 4 small (approximately 15 x 10 cm) colour photographs.
    IMDB page for The Strange Affliction of Anton Bruckner
  - Tommy, 1975; RUS/1/30; Solent University Library; 11 items
    Material relating to Ken Russell's film Tommy. There are 10 black and white photographs showing scenes from the film or during breaks in filming, including some of Russell. There is also a colour program to accompany the film.
    IMDB page for Tommy
  - Treasure Island, 1995; RUS/1/32; Solent University Library; 3 items
    Material relating to Ken Russell's film Treasure Island, which was broadcast by Channel 4 in 1995.
    - A typed 'first draft script', 1 June 1995.
    - What appears to be a draft for a promotional booklet for the film, including a synopsis, short biographies of key cast and crew.
    - A notebook containing a handwritten version of the script.
    IMDB page for Treasure Island
  - Two Women and a Horse, or, St Mawr, 1985; RUS/1/33; Solent University Library; 1 item (109 pages)
    A typewritten script for a screenplay entitled Two Women and a Horse by Ken Russell. It is based on D. H. Lawrence's novella St Mawr.
  - Valentino, 1977; RUS/1/34; Solent University Library; 10 items
    Photographs relating to Ken Russell's film Valentino. There are eight colour photographs that appear to be promotional material, and two black and white photographs of the filming, one showing Russell.
    IMDB page for Valentino
  - Women in Love, 1969; RUS/1/35; Solent University Library; 27 items
    Material relating to Ken Russell's film, Women in Love.
    - 21 black and white photographs taken during filming, some apparently showing scenes from the film, others showing the filming process.
    - Promotional material for the film: 4 colour promotional photographs, 1 promotional booklet ("Exhibitor's Campaign Book"), 1 sheet showing various different advertisements.
    IMDB page for Women in Love
  - Russell's Still Photography, 1958; RUS/1/37; Solent University Library; 10 items
    Still photographs taken by Russell during his time as a professional photographer. There are cuttings from magazines ( Illustrated and The Sketch ) containing his photographs, and one black and white photograph.
    The items are filed under: Ken Russell: friends and family.
- Personal Material, 1958 - 1993; RUS/2; Solent University Library; 16 items
  Material not closely connected to any of Russell's TV and film works. Includes photographs Russell's family and friends, a letter, and newspaper clippings and pamphlets that Russell kept.
  - Photographs, approximately 1972 - 1993; RUS/2/1; Solent University Library; 8 items
    Various photographs owned by Russell that do not relate to a particular one of his works.
    - Five black and white promotional photographs of Dorothy Lamour, taken from her works.
    - One black and white photograph of Ken Russell with director Jack Gold, apparently on stage at a conference.
    - Two black and white photographs, apparently of a shop window display about Ken Russell.
  - Correspondence, 1994; RUS/2/2; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A letter written to Mr Russell from Joanne Deacon (dated 21.03.94); it appears to have originally accompanied a work for Russell to read.
    Items filed under: Ken Russell: Friends and Family
  - Pamphlets, 1956 - 1986; RUS/2/3; Solent University Library; approximately 50 items
    Magazines, brochures, and pamphlets relating to the film industry, including: Critics Choice, programmes from the National Film Theatre, the New Cinema Club, the London Film Festival.
    Held in a box in drawer 4.
  - Film Equipment, approximately 1970; RUS/2/4; Solent University Library; 6 items
    Three empty film tins, one reel of film, one light, one clapperboard.
  - Newspaper Poster, 1986; RUS/2/5; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A newspaper poster for The Sun (Melbourne), approximately 70 x 50 cm, displaying the headline "Spoleto Nudity Shock" and dated Friday, September 12, 1986. It must related to the Spoleto Festival, held in Melbourne for the first time in 1986, at which Russell was an exhibitor.